<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JAC Antimicrob Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JAC Antimicrob Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jacamr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JAC-Antimicrobial Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2632-1823</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11073751</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jacamr/dlae069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dlae069</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Systematic Review</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00740</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01150</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Clinical significance of cefazolin inoculum effect in serious MSSA infections: a systematic review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3664-736X</contrib-id><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>Calvin Ka-Fung</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, University of British Columbia</institution>, <addr-line>Vancouver, BC</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sritharan</surname><given-names>Ashwin</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Michael G. DeGroote Undergraduate School of Medicine, McMaster University</institution>, <addr-line>Hamilton, ON</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jiesi</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Faculty of Health Sciences, Queen&#x2019;s University</institution>, <addr-line>Kingston, ON</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Faculty of Arts and Sciences, Queen's University</institution>, <addr-line>Kingston, ON</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Cindy</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Faculty of Health Sciences, McMaster University</institution>, <addr-line>Hamilton, ON</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Michael G. DeGroote Undergraduate School of Medicine, McMaster University</institution>, <addr-line>Hamilton, ON</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2315-5390</contrib-id><name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Pathology and Molecular Medicine, McMaster University</institution>, <addr-line>Hamilton, ON</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0448-9934</contrib-id><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Anthony D</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, Queen&#x2019;s University</institution>, <addr-line>Kingston, ON</addr-line>, <country country="CA">Canada</country></aff><xref rid="dlae069-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><!--tony.bai@queensu.ca--></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="dlae069-cor1">Corresponding author. E-mail: <email>tony.bai@queensu.ca</email>; <ext-link xlink:href="https://twitter.com/tonybai16" ext-link-type="uri">@tonybai16</ext-link></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2024-05-06"><day>06</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>06</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>dlae069</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of British Society for Antimicrobial Chemotherapy.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="dlae069.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>The cefazolin inoculum effect (CzIE) is a phenomenon whereby some MSSA isolates demonstrate resistance to cefazolin when a high bacterial inoculum is used for susceptibility testing. The clinical significance of this phenotypic phenomenon remains unclear. We conducted a systematic review to answer the following question: In patients with serious MSSA infection treated with cefazolin, does infection due to CzIE-positive MSSA isolates result in worse clinical outcomes than infection due to CzIE-negative MSSA isolates?</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>Ovid MEDLINE, Embase, Cochrane CENTRAL, medRxiv and bioRxiv were searched from inception until 12 April 2023. Studies were included if they tested for CzIE in clinical isolates from MSSA infections in humans. Two independent reviewers extracted data and conducted risk-of-bias assessment. Main outcomes were treatment failure and mortality. Pooling of study estimates was not performed given the heterogeneity of patient populations and outcome definitions.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Twenty-three observational studies were included. CzIE presence amidst MSSA isolates ranged from 0% to 55%. There was no statistically significant mortality difference in two studies that compared MSSA infections with and without CzIE, with ORs ranging from 0.72 to 19.78. Of four studies comparing treatment failure, ORs ranged from 0.26 to 13.00. One study showed a significantly higher treatment failure for the CzIE group, but it did not adjust for potential confounders.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The evidence on CzIE is limited by small observational studies. In these studies, CzIE did not predict higher mortality in MSSA infections treated with cefazolin. Our findings do not support CzIE testing in clinical practice currently.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec id="dlae069-s0">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> can cause serious infections, defined as bacteraemia, pneumonia, pleural space infection, endocarditis, CNS infection, native bone or joint infection, prosthetic joint infection and deep abscesses (visceral organ and intramuscular abscesses).<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B1" ref-type="bibr">1&#x2013;3</xref></sup> Treatment of MSSA infections entails anti-staphylococcal penicillins (e.g. cloxacillin, nafcillin) or a first-generation cephalosporin such as cefazolin.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Although advantages of cefazolin use include more convenient dosing frequency and a reduced risk of nephrotoxicity compared with anti-staphylococcal penicillins such as cloxacillin, concerns exist regarding the presence of a cefazolin inoculum effect (CzIE).<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>When CzIE is present, it suggests the possibility of increased resistance against cefazolin when there is presence of higher bacterial burden. CzIE is an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> phenomenon whereby an MSSA isolate is identified as being susceptible to cefazolin when a standard bacterial concentration is tested, but resistant to cefazolin (i.e. elevation in MIC against cefazolin) when a higher bacterial concentration is used for antibiotic susceptibility testing. More specifically, CzIE is defined as a MIC &#x2264;8&#x2005;mg/L at standard bacterial inoculum of 5&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>5</sup> cfu/mL, and &#x2265;16&#x2005;mg/L at a higher bacterial inoculum of 5&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>7</sup> cfu/mL (i.e. the effect is proportionate to the bacterial inoculum present at site of infection).<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> The CzIE phenomenon is potentially mediated by the &#x3B2;-lactamase enzyme (<italic toggle="yes">blaZ)</italic> gene encoding type A and C &#x3B2;-lactamases in MSSA isolates.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Reportedly, up to 25% of MSSA isolates exhibit CzIE, based on a North American study of 305 blood culture isolates.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> The reference standard for detecting CzIE is broth microdilution, which requires technical expertise beyond that available in routine microbiology laboratories.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> In routine practice, cefazolin susceptibility is inferred from oxacillin or cefoxitin susceptibility testing, molecular detection of <italic toggle="yes">mecA</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">mecC</italic>, or PBP2a assay as per CLSI guidelines.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Thus, routine cefazolin susceptibility testing would not detect CzIE.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>For CzIE-positive deep-seated MSSA infections (endocarditis, bone and joint infection, deep-seated abscesses, osteomyelitis or pneumonia)<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> with a high bacterial burden being treated with cefazolin, there is a theoretical concern that cefazolin will be hydrolysed due to increased production of <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> &#x3B2;-lactamases leading to treatment failure.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> However, the exact mechanism of CzIE and connection with clinical outcomes when detected remains unclear at present.</p>
      <p>To our knowledge, no systematic review has evaluated whether the CzIE is a risk factor for poor patient outcomes with cefazolin treatment. We conducted a systematic review to answer the following question: In patients with serious MSSA infections (bacteraemia, pneumonia, pleural space infection, CNS infection, endocarditis, native bone or joint infection, prosthetic joint infection or deep abscesses) who were treated with cefazolin, does infection due to MSSA isolates that show CzIE result in worse clinical outcomes than infection due to MSSA isolates without CzIE?</p>
      <p>Secondary objectives were to describe: (i) the proportion of MSSA isolates that displayed CzIE across studies; (ii) the diagnostic testing properties of predictors for CzIE; and (iii) the comparison of outcomes in MSSA serious infections with CzIE treated with cefazolin versus an anti-staphylococcal penicillin.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="dlae069-s1">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="dlae069-s1.1">
        <title>Protocol and registration</title>
        <p>This systematic review was prospectively registered on the International Prospective Register of Systematic Reviews (PROSPERO) database (CRD42023420251).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s1.2">
        <title>Search strategy</title>
        <p>Studies were identified by searches across five databases: Ovid MEDLINE, Embase, Cochrane CENTRAL, medRxiv and bioRxiv. The search date range was from inception until 12 April 2023. In collaboration with a research librarian at the University of British Columbia, we developed a search strategy using relevant MeSH search terms to optimize search results (Figure <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>, available as <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> at <italic toggle="yes">JAC-AMR</italic> Online).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s1.3">
        <title>Eligibility criteria and exclusion criteria</title>
        <p>We included all studies published in any language including observational studies (cohort studies, case-control studies, cross-sectional studies) and randomized controlled trials (RCTs) conducted on humans with MSSA infections or studies done on MSSA clinical isolates for which CzIE testing was done. Although this may capture non-serious MSSA infections, this strategy ensured we did not miss studies that cover our secondary objectives.</p>
        <p>Systematic reviews, meta-analyses, case reports, commentaries, letters, abstracts, conference reports or reports of only study design were excluded. Studies that focused strictly on animal models were excluded. Studies primarily focusing on MRSA were excluded as well. If multiple published studies were based on the same patient group and reported the same mortality or treatment failure outcome, only the study describing the largest patient group was selected so that the same patient would not be double counted in the systematic review.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s1.4">
        <title>Data extraction</title>
        <p>Abstracts were screened by two blinded independent authors to identify potentially relevant studies for full-text screening and review. Subsequently, two blinded independent authors read and reviewed the full text for data extraction. Disagreements during study selection and data extraction process were resolved by a third reviewer.</p>
        <p>Data were collected on the following variables:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Journal article information: author, publication year</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Study information: study type, study location, sample size</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Patient information: demographics, risk factors</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Infection: source of clinical isolate, infectious syndrome</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>CzIE testing result and predictors for CzIE used: we defined CzIE as MIC &#x2264;8&#x2005;mg/L at standard inoculum (&#x223C;5&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>5</sup>&#x2005;cfu/mL) and MIC &#x2265;16&#x2005;mg/L at high inoculum (&#x223C;5&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>7</sup>&#x2005;cfu/mL).<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Any surrogate markers for predicting cefazolin resistance or elevated MIC were noted (outside of reference standard of broth microdilution).</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Treatment: antibiotic used as definitive treatment for MSSA infection</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s1.5">
        <title>Outcomes</title>
        <p>The co-primary outcomes were mortality and treatment failure, however defined by the study. Mortality could be all-cause or attributable within the time frame as reported in the study. Treatment failure could include death, complication related to infection, discontinuation of antibiotic treatment due to adverse effects, switch to another antibiotic due to lack of clinical response, and/or recurrence of infection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s1.6">
        <title>Risk-of-bias assessment</title>
        <p>Two reviewers independently assessed the risk of bias with the plan of using the tool that would be most appropriate for the study design and research question: Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS)<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> for observational studies, Cochrane Risk-of-Bias (RoB) Version 2<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> for RCTs, Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) prevalence studies checklist<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> for lab-testing studies, and QUADAS-2 tool<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> for diagnostic accuracy studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s1.7">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The proportion of CzIE in samples was calculated for each study. In a <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> analysis, we described the prevalence of CzIE in studies categorized by country and continent.</p>
        <p>For diagnostic parameters of CzIE predictors, we calculated the sensitivity, specificity and likelihood ratios with corresponding 95% CIs for each study in comparison with the listed reference standard (i.e. broth micro or macro-dilution). In 2&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;2 tables with a zero in one cell, 0.5 was added to all cells before doing the calculations.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></p>
        <p>There was significant clinical heterogeneity in terms of how the patient population and outcomes were defined across studies. Therefore, only a descriptive analysis of individual studies was done. For each study, we compared the mortality and treatment failure as defined by the study between MSSA isolates with CzIE and MSSA isolates without CzIE in patients with MSSA infections who were treated with cefazolin. We calculated the unadjusted OR with MSSA isolates without CzIE as the reference and 95% CI for mortality and treatment failure. We also reported the adjusted ORs if provided by the study.</p>
        <p>Data analysis was performed using the statistical software SPSS ver27 2020 and R.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="dlae069-s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="dlae069-s2.1">
        <title>Study selection and description of included studies</title>
        <p>The literature search yielded 1077 records (Figure <xref rid="dlae069-F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). A total of 271 duplicates were removed, resulting in 806 unique records that were screened. After abstract screening and full-text reading, 23 studies were included in the analysis (Table <xref rid="dlae069-T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B6" ref-type="bibr">6&#x2013;8</xref>,<xref rid="dlae069-B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="dlae069-B16" ref-type="bibr">16&#x2013;34</xref></sup> Excluded studies and corresponding exclusion reasons are listed in Table <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>.</p>
        <fig position="float" id="dlae069-F1" fig-type="figure">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Flow diagram for inclusion of studies.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="dlae069f1" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="dlae069-T1">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Study characteristics: study type, geographical location, cefazolin inoculum effect (CzIE) proportion and infection type across included studies (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;23)</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study reference no.</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study design<break/>Centre Year<break/>Location</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient population<break/>CzIE-positive group<break/>CzIE-negative group</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary outcome</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conclusion</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort<break/>Single centre<break/>2013&#x2013;2018<break/>France</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA endocarditis (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;51)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;4) treated with cefazolin<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;16) treated with cefazolin</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent bacteraemia on treatment &#x2265;72&#x2005;h<break/>Clinical failure at 3 mo based on worsening on therapy, septic embolism, discontinuation of treatment due to adverse events, relapse or death</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE was not associated with increased risk for clinical failure on treatment</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Multicentre<break/>2010&#x2013;2014, 2018&#x2013;2019<break/>Latin America</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;690)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;278)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;412)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between allotypes of BlaZ and CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Certain allotypes were more associated with CzIE, whereas others were not</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>2011&#x2013;2018<break/>USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with haematogenous MSSA osteomyelitis (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;250)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;36)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;214)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Progression to chronic osteomyelitis</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE is independently associated with progression to chronic osteomyelitis irrespective of final antibiotic choice</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort<break/>Single centre<break/>2008&#x2013;2011<break/>South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;220), of which 77 patients were treated with cefazolin<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;29)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=&#x200A;191)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment failure defined as: (i) a change of antibiotics due to clinical failure during treatment, (ii) relapse of MSSA infection after apparently successful completion of treatment or (iii) MSSA bacteraemia-attributable mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE was not associated with increased risk for clinical failure on treatment</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Multicentre<break/>2019<break/>USA, Canada</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;305)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;57)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;248)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of CzIE and its association with &#x3B2;-lactamase types</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE was present in up to 25% of clinical MSSA isolates. Most common <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> &#x3B2;-lactamases found in CzIE strains were type A and C</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Single centre<break/>1976<break/>USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA clinical isolates not otherwise specified (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;100)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between inoculum size and MIC of different cephalosporins</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Different cephalosporins are inactivated with increasing bacterial inoculum resulting in high MICs. The clinical significance of this phenomenon is not known</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Multicentre<break/>2004&#x2013;2013<break/>South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA blood isolates (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;113)<break/>Of 17 strains positive for type A <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene, 10 tested positive for CzIE and 7 tested negative</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between type A <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> polymorphism and CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The SNP at codon 226 and 229 encoded by <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene is closely associated with CzIE</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>2004&#x2013;2013<break/>South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia treated with cefazolin (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;113)<break/>Of 113 cases, 23 (20.4%) displayed CzIE based on increase in MIC to &#x2265;16&#x2005;mg/L at high inoculum</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment failure defined as: (i) switching of antibiotics due to the clinician&#x2019;s decision of the treatment failure; (ii) recurrence of MSSA infection; or (iii) MSSA bacteraemia-associated mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE may be associated with persistent bacteraemia, but not significantly associated with treatment failure</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>2013&#x2013;2015<break/>South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;242)<break/>In the propensity score-matched cohort of 110 cases, 24 were CzIE positive and 86 were CzIE negative</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment failure defined as: (i) switching antibiotics because treatment had failed in the clinician's opinion; (ii) premature discontinuation of antibiotics because of adverse effects; (iii) all-cause mortality within 1 mo; or (iv) recurrence or relapse of MSSA infection within 3 mo of treatment completion</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE is associated with cefazolin treatment failure for MSSA bacteraemia</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Single centre<break/>2014&#x2013;2017<break/>South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA blood isolates (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;195)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;23)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;172)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> genotype and CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type A <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> genotype with <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic> type III could be a useful indicator to genetically differentiate CzIE-positive MSSA isolates</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>2010&#x2013;2010<break/>USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA isolates from bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;185), of which 8 (4%) demonstrated CzIE based on increase in MIC to &#x2265;16&#x2005;mg/L at high inoculum</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene types and CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene was present in 142/185 (77%) isolates. There were 50 isolates that had &#x2265;4-fold increase in MIC and 8 (4%) had a non-susceptible cefazolin MIC at high inoculum, which were all type A <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> strains</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>2011&#x2013;2014<break/>Argentina</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;77)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;42)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;35)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 d mortality, treatment failure</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE was associated with increased 30 d mortality when cephalosporins are used as first-line therapy for MSSA bacteraemia</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Multicentre<break/>2011<break/>Japan</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA clinical isolates from sputum, pharynx and blood (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;49)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association between inoculum and MIC for different antibiotics</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There were small fluctuations in cefazolin MIC when increasing inoculum was used</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Multicentre<break/>1981&#x2013;2017<break/>Canada</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA isolates from sputum culture in non-cystic fibrosis bronchiectasis (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;60)<break/>Of 60 isolates, there were no cases of pronounced CzIE based on increase in MIC to &#x2265;16&#x2005;mg/L at high inoculum</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To describe the prevalence of inoculum effect for different antibiotics</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inoculum-related resistance was relevant for commonly used antibiotics such as cefazolin and piperacillin/tazobactam</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>Not specified<break/>Not specified</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical isolates from endocarditis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;29), pneumonia (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;29), skin and soft tissue infection (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;28), and bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;12). Of the 98 isolates, 19 (19.2%) displayed CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association of CzIE with the type of &#x3B2;-lactamases<break/>Treatment failure</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE was found in 19 cases, of which 10 were type C &#x3B2;-lactamase producers and 9 were type A &#x3B2;-lactamase producers. There was an association between CzIE and cefazolin failure in haemodialysis patients with bacteraemia</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnostic accuracy<break/>Multicentre<break/>2011&#x2013;2019<break/>Latin America and USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA isolates from blood culture (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;689)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;257)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;432)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnostic accuracy of a colorimetric test to detect CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rapid colorimetric test can accurately detect CzIE with sensitivity of 82.5% and specificity of 88.9%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Multicentre<break/>2001&#x2013;2008<break/>South America</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA isolates from bloodstream (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;296) and osteomyelitis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;68)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;131)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;233)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of CzIE across South American hospitals</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">There is a high prevalence of CzIE associated with type A &#x3B2;-lactamase in Colombia and Ecuador</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Single centre<break/>1975<break/>USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical MSSA isolates (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;118) not otherwise specified. CzIE status was not specified</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine the inoculum effect on the anti-staphylococcal &#x3B2;-lactams</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Of tested &#x3B2;-lactams, cefazolin was more susceptible to inoculum effect than other cephalosporins</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Single centre<break/>2012&#x2013;2014<break/>Japan</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA isolates from blood culture (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;52), of which 3 (5.8%) had pronounced CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inoculum effect to different &#x3B2;-lactams</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inoculum effect was found for cefazolin and ampicillin/sulbactam, but not cefotaxime, ceftriaxone, imipenem and meropenem</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>2013&#x2013;2015<break/>South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;303)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;61)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;242)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics of CzIE-positive isolates</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythromycin and clindamycin resistance were predictors of CzIE</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Single centre<break/>2019<break/>Russia</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA isolates from skin/soft tissue infection (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;80), of which 2 (2.5%) displayed CzIE based on increase in MIC to &#x2265;16&#x2005;mg/L at high inoculum</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of CzIE and its association with penicillin resistance</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE is associated with penicillin resistance and &#x3B2;-lactamase <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lab testing<break/>Multicentre<break/>2014&#x2013;2015<break/>USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSSA clinical isolates from any sites (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;269), of which 5 (3%) displayed pronounced CzIE</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association with <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene types and CzIE in MSSA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The local prevalence of pronounced CzIE was low</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort<break/>Multicentre<break/>2011&#x2013;2012<break/>South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with MSSA bacteraemia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;146)<break/>CzIE-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;16)<break/>CzIE-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x200A;=&#x200A;130)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Association of CzIE with &#x3B2;-lactamase types and dysfunctional accessory gene regulator (<italic toggle="yes">agr</italic>)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CzIE was associated with type A &#x3B2;-lactamase and dysfunctional <italic toggle="yes">agr</italic></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s2.2">
        <title>Risk-of-bias assessment</title>
        <p>Risk-of-bias assessment is described in Table <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> for 10 cohort studies, Table <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref> for 12 lab-testing studies and Table <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref> for one diagnostic accuracy study. For cohort studies, each study was rated on an overall score from 1 to 9, with 6&#x2013;9 being high quality, 3&#x2013;5 being fair and 0&#x2013;2 being poor quality.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Nine studies scored at least 6 points. The remaining study had a score of 4. Of note, there were no eligible RCTs and hence the RoB Version 2 tool was not applicable in our assessment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s2.3">
        <title>Proportion of MSSA isolates that displayed CzIE</title>
        <p>There were 19 studies that reported the proportion of MSSA isolates displaying CzIE as defined by MIC &#x2264;8&#x2005;mg/L at standard inoculum and MIC &#x2265;16&#x2005;mg/L at high inoculum (Table <xref rid="dlae069-T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The median number of isolates per study was 185 (range 51 to 690), with a median of 14.4% of isolates being positive for CzIE (range 0% to 54.5%). The proportion of CzIE in MSSA ranged from 0% to 18.7% in North American countries, 36.0% to 54.5% in South American countries, 2.5% to 11.0% in European countries, and 5.8% to 21.8% in Asian countries.</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="dlae069-T2">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Proportion of MSSA isolates that tested positive for cefazolin inoculum effect (CzIE) in studies categorized by country and continent<sup><xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></sup></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Continent</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study reference</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolates tested for CzIE, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic></th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolates with CzIE, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (14.4)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4.3)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2.6)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA, Canada</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (18.7)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South America</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Argentina</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (54.5)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, Venezuela</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">364</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (36.0)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">North and South America</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mexico, Colombia, Peru, Argentina, Ecuador, Chile, Brazil, Guatemala, Venezuela</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">690</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (40.3)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mexico, Colombia, Peru, Argentina, Ecuador, Chile, Brazil, Guatemala, Venezuela, USA</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">689</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257 (37.3)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.9)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (11.0)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.5)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (13.2)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (20.4)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (21.8)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (11.8)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">303</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (20.1)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.8)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tblfn1">
              <p>
<sup>a</sup>Study reference 10 was not included because the country of origin for the MSSA isolates was unclear. In this study, 19/98 (19.2%) displayed CzIE. Study reference 20 was not included because the testing method and definition for CzIE are different from our definition. Study reference 21 was not included because it tested only MSSA isolates that tested positive for type A <italic toggle="yes">blaZ</italic> gene.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s2.4">
        <title>Surrogate predictors for CzIE</title>
        <p>Three studies reported predictors for CzIE that allowed calculation of diagnostic properties. Surrogate predictors included erythromycin resistance, clindamycin resistance, and a rapid colorimetric testing. Diagnostic properties are summarized in Table <xref rid="dlae069-T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The rapid colorimetric test specifically designed for detection of CzIE<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> had the best combination of sensitivity and specificity based on the point estimate and CI.</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="dlae069-T3">
          <label>Table 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Diagnostic properties of surrogate predictors for cefazolin inoculum effect (CzIE)</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screening test</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study reference</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">True positive</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">False negative</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">False positive</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">True negative</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity, % (95% CI)<break/>Specificity, % (95% CI)<break/>Positive likelihood ratio (95% CI)<break/>Negative likelihood ratio (95% CI)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythromycin resistance</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn: 32.8 (22.3&#x2013;45.3)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp: 90.9 (86.6&#x2013;93.9)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLR: 3.6 (2.1&#x2013;6.2)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR: 0.74 (0.62&#x2013;0.89)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clindamycin resistance</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn: 25.0 (13.8&#x2013;41.1)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp: 90.7 (86.0&#x2013;93.9)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLR: 2.7 (1.3&#x2013;5.4)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR: 0.83 (0.68&#x2013;1.00)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn: 21.3 (12.9&#x2013;33.1)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp: 93.0 (89.0&#x2013;95.6)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLR: 3.0 (1.6&#x2013;5.9)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR: 0.85 (0.74&#x2013;0.97)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rapid colorimetric test</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">384</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn: 82.5 (77.4&#x2013;86.6)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp: 88.9 (85.6&#x2013;91.5)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLR: 7.4 (5.7&#x2013;9.8)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR: 0.20 (0.15&#x2013;0.26)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tblfn2">
              <p>NLR, negative likelihood ratio; PLR, positive likelihood ratio; Sn, sensitivity; Sp, specificity.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s2.5">
        <title>Mortality and treatment failure</title>
        <p>Only two studies reported mortality outcomes (Table <xref rid="dlae069-T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The mortality definition varied in terms of timepoint, which ranged from 1 month to 3 months. The wide 95% CIs reflect small number sizes and inconclusive results. No study showed a significant difference in mortality between CzIE-positive and -negative MSSA infections.</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="dlae069-T4">
          <label>Table 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Clinical outcomes comparing CzIE-positive versus CzIE-negative isolates for MSSA infections treated with cefazolin</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Events in CzIE-positive group</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Events in CzIE-negative group</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR for CzIE (95% CI)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 d all-cause mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/10 (10.0%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/67 (13.4%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.72 (0.08&#x2013;6.35)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 wk all-cause mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/10 (20.0%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/67 (17.9%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.15 (0.22&#x2013;6.09)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 mo all-cause mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/13 (15.4%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/45 (0%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 19.78 (0.89&#x2013;441.14)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 mo all-cause mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/13 (15.4%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/45 (0%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 19.78 (0.89&#x2013;441.14)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment failure</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotic switch, relapse post-treatment or infection related mortality</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10 (0%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/67 (14.9%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 0.26 (0.01&#x2013;4.80)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotic switch, infection recurrence or infection-related death within 12 wk</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 1.39 (0.45&#x2013;4.32)<break/>aOR: 1.30 (0.35&#x2013;4.88)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotic switch, death within 1 mo, recurrence within 3 mo, discontinuation from adverse events</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/13 (61.5%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/45 (28.9%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 3.93 (1.08&#x2013;14.31)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relapse and infection-related mortality<break/>(no time period was specified for outcome)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/3 (100%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/9 (33.3%)</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR: 13.00 (0.51&#x2013;330.50)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="tblfn3">
              <p>aOR, adjusted odds ratio, otherwise OR refers to unadjusted odds ratios; CzIE, cefazolin inoculum effect.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Four studies reported treatment failure outcomes (Table <xref rid="dlae069-T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The definition for treatment failure varied across studies. A single study found a statistically significant increase in treatment failure for CzIE-positive isolates with an OR of 3.93 (95% CI: 1.08 to 14.31) (Table <xref rid="dlae069-T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> In this study, there was no adjustment for potential confounders in the subgroup analysis when the CzIE-positive group was compared with the CzIE-negative group.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dlae069-s2.6">
        <title>Cefazolin versus anti-staphylococcal penicillin for CzIE-positive MSSA infections</title>
        <p>One study compared the mortality and treatment failure between an anti-staphylococcal penicillin and cefazolin for CzIE-positive MSSA infections.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> At the end of 1 month and 3 months, 2/13 (15.4%) patients in the cefazolin group and 1/11 (9.1%) patients in the nafcillin group died (OR 1.82; 95% CI: 0.14 to 23.26).<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Treatment failure, defined as discontinuation of antibiotics due to adverse effects, antibiotic change due to clinical failure, death within 1 month and recurrence, occurred in 8/13 (61.5%) for the cefazolin group and 4/11 (36.4%) patients for the nafcillin group (OR 2.80; 95% CI: 0.53 to 14.74).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="dlae069-s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our results show that the clinical impact of CzIE is based on small observational studies that provide poor quality evidence. Overall, the proportion of MSSA infections displaying CzIE ranged from 0% to 55% across studies. No study found a significant difference in mortality between CzIE-positive and -negative MSSA infections treated with cefazolin. All but one study found no significant difference in treatment failure between CzIE-positive and -negative MSSA infections treated with cefazolin. Therefore, there is a lack of evidence to support that CzIE is clinically important currently.</p>
      <p>Strengths of our review included a comprehensive search of multiple databases that included preprints and had no language restrictions. There was also rigorous screening and data collection by two independent reviewers for each study.</p>
      <p>Limitations included the very limited sample size pool of four studies that reported mortality and treatment outcomes.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="dlae069-B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="dlae069-B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="dlae069-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Most studies did not adjust for potential confounders. There was significant heterogeneity across studies for types of infections and definition of outcomes. Only one study reported clinical outcomes for anti-staphylococcal penicillins.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> It is important to compare the effectiveness of cefazolin versus anti-staphylococcal penicillin in the treatment of MSSA infection with CzIE. The rationale is that if MSSA infections with CzIE treated with cefazolin had worse outcomes than MSSA infections without CzIE treated with cefazolin, there may be a reason other than cefazolin treatment and CzIE for the difference in outcome. MSSA isolates that display CzIE may also have other intrinsic bacterial characteristics that make the isolates more virulent and the infection more deadly regardless of antibiotic treatment choice. If that is the case, then MSSA with CzIE treated with cefazolin versus an anti-staphylococcal penicillin would have similar outcomes.</p>
      <p>Large studies are needed to provide higher quality evidence on whether CzIE is clinically important. The ideal study should include serious and deep-seated infections in which CzIE may be clinically relevant. MSSA infections with CzIE treated with cefazolin should be compared with MSSA infections without CzIE treated with cefazolin as well as MSSA infections with CzIE treated with an anti-staphylococcal penicillin. Lastly, adjustment should be made for potential confounders.</p>
      <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="dlae069-s3.1">
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>In conclusion, there is very low quality of evidence at present that does not support the theory that CzIE translates to worse outcomes in terms of mortality or treatment failure for serious MSSA infections being treated with cefazolin. Thus, our study supports the CLSI recommendation that CzIE should not be tested in clinical settings outside of research until there is more evidence to suggest otherwise.<sup><xref rid="dlae069-B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="dlae069-B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> Clinical microbiology laboratories should avoid routine testing for CzIE when pursuing microbiological workup of MSSA clinical isolates, because the current evidence does not support the use of CzIE results when making clinical treatment decisions for MSSA infections.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data">
        <label>dlae069_Supplementary_Data</label>
        <media xlink:href="dlae069_supplementary_data.docx"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack id="ack1">
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Vanessa Kitchin (University of British Columbia) for reviewing and providing feedback in development of our search strategy.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="dlae069-s4">
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This study was carried out as part of our routine work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="dlae069-s5">
      <title>Transparency declarations</title>
      <p>None to declare. All authors declare no competing interests associated with this study.</p>
      <sec id="dlae069-s5.2">
        <title>Author contributions</title>
        <p>C.K.-F.L., M.L. and A.D.B. conceived and designed the study; C.K.-F.L., A.S., J.Z., N.L., C.Z., F.W. and A.D.B. performed the data collection; C.K.-F.L. and A.S. performed the analysis. C.K.-F.L., A.S. and A.D.B. jointly wrote the first draft of the manuscript. All authors reviewed the full data set prior to publication and take responsibility for its accuracy. All authors reviewed and revised the manuscript and approved a final version for publication submission.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="dlae069-s5.1">
      <title>Data availability</title>
      <p>Data and material are available and will be provided upon request from the corresponding author.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="dlae069-s6">
      <title>Supplementary data</title>
      <p>Figure <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> and Tables <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 to S4</xref> are available as <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary data</xref> at <italic toggle="yes">JAC-AMR</italic> Online.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list id="ref1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="dlae069-B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Que</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>Y-A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moreillon</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <part-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (including staphylococcal toxic shock syndrome)</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Bennett</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dolin</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blaser</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>, eds. <source>Mandell, Douglas, and Bennett's Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases E-Book</source>. <publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name>, <year>2019;</year> &#xA0;<fpage>2393</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>431</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bayer</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cosgrove</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Clinical practice guidelines by the Infectious Diseases Society of America for the treatment of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections in adults and children</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source> &#xA0;<year>2011</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>e18</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciq146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21208910</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rybak</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lodise</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>TP</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Therapeutic monitoring of vancomycin for serious methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections: a revised consensus guideline and review by the American Society of Health-System Pharmacists, Infectious Diseases Society of America, Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society, and the Society of Infectious Diseases Pharmacists</article-title>. <source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source> &#xA0;<year>2020</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>835</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajhp/zxaa036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Echevarria</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Traugott</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>&#x3B2;-Lactam therapy for methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteremia: a comparative review of cefazolin versus antistaphylococcal penicillins</article-title>. <source>Pharmacotherapy</source> &#xA0;<year>2017</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>346</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/phar.1892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28035690</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Weis</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kesselmeier</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davis</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Cefazolin versus anti-staphylococcal penicillins for the treatment of patients with <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteraemia</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source> &#xA0;<year>2019</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>818</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2019.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30928559</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dingle</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamage</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gomez-Villegas</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Prevalence and characterization of the cefazolin inoculum effect in North American methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source> &#xA0;<year>2022</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>e02495-21</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jcm.02495-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35578988</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwon</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>H-I</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Clinical implications of cefazolin inoculum effect and &#x3B2;-lactamase type on methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteremia</article-title>. <source>Microbial Drug Resist</source> &#xA0;<year>2014</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2013.0229</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rinc&#xF3;n</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reyes</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carvajal</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Cefazolin high-inoculum effect in methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> from South American hospitals</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2013</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>2773</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkt254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23794599</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rao</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhodes</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Treatment outcomes with cefazolin versus oxacillin for deep-seated methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bloodstream infections</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2015</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>5232</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.04677-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26077253</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nannini</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stryjewski</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>KV</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Inoculum effect with cefazolin among clinical isolates of methicillin-susceptible S<italic toggle="yes">taphylococcus aureus</italic>: frequency and possible cause of cefazolin treatment failure</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2009</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>3437</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00317-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19487449</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wells</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shea</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O'Connell</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) for assessing the quality of nonrandomized studies in meta-analyses. The Ottawa Hospital. <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.ohri.ca/programs/clinical_epidemiology/oxford.asp" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ohri.ca/programs/clinical_epidemiology/oxford.asp</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Higgins</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savovi&#x107;</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Page</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<part-title>Assessing risk of bias in a randomized trial</part-title>. <source>Cochrane Collaboration</source>, <year>2019</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://training.cochrane.org/handbook/current/chapter-08" ext-link-type="uri">https://training.cochrane.org/handbook/current/chapter-08</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Munn</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moola</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lisy</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<part-title>Chapter 5: systematic reviews of prevalence and incidence</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Aromataris</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munn</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group>, eds. <source>JBI Manual for Evidence Synthesis</source>. <publisher-name>JBI</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>; <fpage>177</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>217</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Whiting</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>PF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rutjes</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westwood</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>QUADAS-2: a revised tool for the quality assessment of diagnostic accuracy studies</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> &#xA0;<year>2011</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-155-8-201110180-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22007046</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Weber</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knapp</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ickstadt</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Zero-cell corrections in random-effects meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>Res Synth Methods</source> &#xA0;<year>2020</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>913</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jrsm.1460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32991790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bourreau</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le Mabecque</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broquet</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Prevalence of a cefazolin inoculum effect associated with blaZ gene types, and clinical outcomes among methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> blood isolates of patients with infective endocarditis</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Now</source> &#xA0;<year>2023</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>104626</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idnow.2022.09.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36184048</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Carvajal</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rincon</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Echeverri</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Novel insights into the classification of staphylococcal &#x3B2;-lactamases in relation to the cefazolin inoculum effect</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2020</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>e02511-19</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02511-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32071048</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>McNeil</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sommer</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boyle</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Cefazolin inoculum effect and methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> osteoarticular infections in children</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2020</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>e00703-20</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00703-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32660989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chong</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>YP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Prevalence of blaZ gene types and the cefazolin inoculum effect among methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> blood isolates and their association with multilocus sequence types and clinical outcome</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source> &#xA0;<year>2015</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-014-2241-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25213722</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fong</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>IW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engelking</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirby</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>WM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Relative inactivation by <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> of eight cephalosporin antibiotics</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>1976</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.9.6.939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">938023</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Association between type A blaZ gene polymorphism and cefazolin inoculum effect in methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2016</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>6928</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01517-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27572417</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Comparative outcomes of cefazolin versus nafcillin for methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteraemia: a prospective multicentre cohort study in Korea</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source> &#xA0;<year>2018</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2017.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28694202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B23">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>The cefazolin inoculum effect and the presence of type A blaZ gene according to agr genotype in methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteremia</article-title>. <source>Infect Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2019</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3947/ic.2019.51.4.376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31898425</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B24">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Livorsi</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crispell</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Satola</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Prevalence of blaZ gene types and the inoculum effect with cefazolin among bloodstream isolates of methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2012</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>4474</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00052-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22585225</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B25">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seas</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carvajal</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>The cefazolin inoculum effect is associated with increased mortality in methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteremia</article-title>. <source>Open Forum Infect Dis</source> &#xA0;<year>2018</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>ofy123</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofy123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29977970</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B26">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Miyake</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kadowaki</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Influence of inoculum size on MICs for methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Jpn J Antibiot</source> &#xA0;<year>2011</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22066347</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B27">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Mossman</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svishchuk</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waddell</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>BJM</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in non-cystic fibrosis bronchiectasis: prevalence and genomic basis of high inoculum &#x3B2;-lactam resistance</article-title>. <source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source> &#xA0;<year>2022</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202108-965OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35213810</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B28">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rincon</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carvajal</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gomez-Villegas</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>A test for the rapid detection of the cefazolin inoculum effect in methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source> &#xA0;<year>2021</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>e01938-20</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01938-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33536292</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B29">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sabath</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garner</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilcox</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Effect of inoculum and of beta-lactamase on the anti-staphylococcal activity of thirteen penicillins and cephalosporins</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>1975</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.8.3.344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1167043</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B30">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Saeki</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shinagawa</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yakuwa</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Inoculum effect of high concentrations of methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> on the efficacy of cefazolin and other beta-lactams</article-title>. <source>J Infect Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2018</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2017.10.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29198902</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B31">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Song</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Characteristics of cefazolin inoculum effect-positive methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infection in a multicentre bacteraemia cohort</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source> &#xA0;<year>2017</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-016-2799-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27714592</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B32">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Vaganova</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borisenko</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nesterova</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Cefazolin inoculum effect among methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from patients with skin infections</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Antimicrob Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2021</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B33">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gilchrist</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loukitcheva</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>Prevalence of a cefazolin inoculum effect associated with blaZ gene types among methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates from four major medical centers in Chicago</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> &#xA0;<year>2018</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>e00382-18</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00382-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29891607</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B34">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wi</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moon</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name> &#xA0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#xA0;<article-title>The cefazolin inoculum effect in methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> blood isolates: their association with dysfunctional accessory gene regulator (agr)</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source> &#xA0;<year>2015</year>; <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>286</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2015.07.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26277619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B35">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>CLSI</collab>
</person-group>. <source>Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing&#x2014;Twenty-Seventh Edition: M100</source>. <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="dlae069-B36">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arias</surname> &#xA0;<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. The cefazolin inoculum effect for MSSA. CLSI, 2019. <ext-link xlink:href="https://clsi.org/about/blog/ast-news-update-2019-hot-topic/" ext-link-type="uri">https://clsi.org/about/blog/ast-news-update-2019-hot-topic/</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>